[
    {
        "question": "Which companies were granted 'Navratna Status' by the central government?",
        "options": [
            "IRCTC and NTPC.",
            "IRFC and ONGC.",
            "IRCTC and IRFC.",
            "NTPC and ONGC."
        ],
        "answer": "IRCTC and IRFC."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is the recipient of the Gangadhar National Award for Poetry 2023?",
        "options": [
            "Sitakant Mahapatra",
            "Prativa Satpathy",
            "Jayanta Mahapatra",
            "Ramakanta Rath",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which legendary cricketer was awarded honorary membership of the Melbourne Cricket Club (MCC)?",
        "options": [
            "Sunil Gavaskar",
            "Sachin Tendulkar",
            "Kapil Dev",
            "Sourav Ganguly"
        ],
        "answer": "Sachin Tendulkar"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was crowned the 'Spell Master of India' in SBI Life Spell Bee Season 14?",
        "options": [
            "Medhansh Vaddadi",
            "Yashwin Pachauri",
            "Chaya M V",
            "Mandira Bedi",
            "Sakshi Sinha"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which award will Taika Waititi receive at the 36th Producers Guild of America Awards?",
        "options": [
            "Academy Award",
            "Golden Globe Award",
            "Grammy Award",
            "Norman Lear Achievement Award",
            "Pen Pinter Prize"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "What were the key contributions of S. M. Krishna to Indian politics, and which prestigious award was he honored with in 2023?",
        "options": [
            "Transforming Bengaluru into India's Silicon Valley; Padma Shri",
            "Establishing Karnataka as a leading agricultural state; Bharat Ratna",
            "Advocating for women's empowerment and rural development; Padma Bhushan",
            "Serving as Chief Minister of Karnataka and Minister of External Affairs; Padma Vibhushan",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which prestigious award has Indian environmentalist Madhav Gadgil received in 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Nobel Prize for Environmental Science",
            "UNEP's Lifetime Achievement Award",
            "Tyler Prize for Environmental Achievement",
            "Padma Bhushan",
            "Environment Engineer Award"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which state was awarded the Geographical Indication (GI) tag for its traditional handicraft, 'Gharchola,' known for its intricate designs and cultural motifs?",
        "options": [
            "Rajasthan",
            "Gujarat",
            "Punjab",
            "Maharashtra",
            "Haryana"
        ],
        "answer": "Gujarat"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was awarded the Indian Film Personality of the Year at the 55th International Film Festival of India (IFFI)?",
        "options": [
            "Amitabh Bachchan",
            "Rajinikanth",
            "Vikrant Massey",
            "Nawazuddin Siddiqui",
            "Deepika Padukone"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was crowned Miss India USA 2024 at the event held in New Jersey?",
        "options": [
            "Nirali Desia",
            "Manini Patel",
            "Sanskriti Sharma",
            "Caitlin Sandra Neil",
            "Shipra Negi"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was awarded the Indira Gandhi Prize for Peace, Disarmament, and Development 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Ban Ki-moon",
            "Angela Merkel",
            "Veronica Michelle Bachelet",
            "Jacinda Ardern",
            "Malala Yousafzai"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who posthumously honored Dr. Vishakha Tripathi Ji with the Lifetime Achievement Award for her extraordinary service to humanity?",
        "options": [
            "World Health Organization (WHO)",
            "Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR)",
            "United Nations Development Program (UNDP)",
            "Asia Pacific Vascular Society (APVS)",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was awarded the Jamsetji Tata Award for pioneering the biosciences movement in India?",
        "options": [
            "Ratan Tata",
            "Janak Kumar Mehta",
            "Kiran Mazumdar-Shaw",
            "B Muthuraman",
            "Adar Poonawala"
        ],
        "answer": "Kiran Mazumdar-Shaw"
    },
    {
        "question": "India received the ISSA Good Practice Award for Asia-Pacific 2024 for which purpose?",
        "options": [
            "Launching a nationwide pension scheme",
            "Enhancing agricultural productivity",
            "Innovative activities of the Employees' Provident Fund Organisation (EPFO)",
            "Advancing renewable energy technologies",
            "Developing multilingual education platforms"
        ],
        "answer": "Innovative activities of the Employees' Provident Fund Organisation (EPFO)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which company won two awards at the 3rd PSU Transformation Awards 2024 for Innovative Product Development and Technology Adoption?",
        "options": [
            "Cochin Shipyard Limited",
            "Hindustan Shipyard Limited",
            "Mazagon Dock Shipbuilders Limited",
            "Garden Reach Shipbuilders & Engineers",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Hindustan Shipyard Limited"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who will receive the Lifetime Achievement Award at the 77th Annual Directors Guild of America (DGA) Awards, and what makes their contributions significant?",
        "options": [
            "Steven Spielberg; known for his blockbuster films and innovative techniques",
            "Ang Lee; recognized for his diverse filmmaking and cinematic excellence",
            "Martin Scorsese; celebrated for his contribution to crime and drama genres",
            "Ridley Scott; honored for his work in science fiction and historical epics",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Which researcher from the Zoological Survey of India (ZSI) is credited with discovering the new species of pangolin, named the Indo-Burmese pangolin (Manis indoburmanica), in Arunachal Pradesh?",
        "options": [
            "Lenrik Konchok",
            "Suresh Naik",
            "Ramesh Pandey",
            "Deepa Sharma",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been named the ICC Men's ODI Cricketer of the Year 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Rashid Khan",
            "Azmatullah Omarzai",
            "Babar Azam",
            "Rohit Sharma",
            "Jasprit Bumrah"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who won the Dronacharya Award for outstanding coaches in Sports and Games 2024 in the Regular Category for Hockey?",
        "options": [
            "Shri Harendra Singh",
            "Shri Sandeep Sangwan",
            "Shri Randhir Singh Gentle",
            "Shri Harmik Singh",
            "Shri Yograj Singh"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which university was honored with the prestigious MAKA Trophy 2024 and had a student, Sanjay Kumar, receive the Arjuna Award for hockey?",
        "options": [
            "Amity University",
            "Chandigarh University",
            "Banaras Hindu University",
            "Delhi University",
            "LPU"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which former Indian hockey player received the Padma Bhushan award on the eve of the 76th Republic Day?",
        "options": [
            "R Ashwin",
            "Inivalappil Mani Vijayan",
            "Harvinder Singh",
            "PR Sreejesh",
            "Manpreet Singh"
        ],
        "answer": "PR Sreejesh"
    },
    {
        "question": "Christine Carla Kangaloo, President of _________, was awarded the Pravasi Bharatiya Samman Award 2025.",
        "options": [
            "Guyana",
            "Trinidad and Tobago",
            "Fiji",
            "Mauritius",
            "Algeria"
        ],
        "answer": "Trinidad and Tobago"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is the recipient of the Major Dhyan Chand Khel Ratna Award 2024 for his outstanding contribution to sports?",
        "options": [
            "Virat Kohli",
            "Neeraj Chopra",
            "Manika Batra",
            "Harmanpreet Singh",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was crowned the ICC Women's ODI Cricketer of the Year for 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Laura Wolvaardt",
            "Tammy Beaumont",
            "Hayley Matthews",
            "\u200bSmriti Mandhana",
            "None of the abocve"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was awarded the JC Daniel Award 2023 for lifetime contributions to Malayalam cinema, and what are some of his notable achievements?",
        "options": [
            "TV Chandran for pioneering new-wave cinema",
            "KS Chitra for contributions to music in Malayalam films",
            "Shaji N Karun for showcasing Malayalam cinema on the international stage",
            "Vijayaraghavan for his acting in Malayalam cinema",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Shaji N Karun for showcasing Malayalam cinema on the international stage"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who won the gold medal in the 25m women's pistol event at the National Shooting Championships?",
        "options": [
            "Heena Sidhu",
            "Rahi Sarnobat",
            "Simranpreet Kaur Brar",
            "Riya Shirish Thatte",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been named TIME's 2024 Person of the Year?",
        "options": [
            "Donald Trump",
            "Elon Musk",
            "Volodymyr Zelenskyy",
            "Vladimir Putin",
            "Malala Yousufzhai"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which English news channel won the 'Best News Channel (English)' award at the ITA Awards 2024?",
        "options": [
            "NDTV",
            "Republic TV",
            "India Today",
            "CNN-News18",
            "Times Now"
        ],
        "answer": "India Today"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country has been awarded the hosting rights for the ISSF Junior Shooting World Cup 2025?",
        "options": [
            "China",
            "Germany",
            "India",
            "South Korea",
            "Italy"
        ],
        "answer": "India"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was awarded the Sahitya Akademi Award 2024 in Dogri for the book 'Ik Hor Ashwthama'?",
        "options": [
            "Shashi Tharoor",
            "Gajanan Madhav Muktibodh",
            "Uday Prakash",
            "Chaman Arora",
            "Nand Kishore"
        ],
        "answer": "Chaman Arora"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which film won the NETPAC Award at the International Film Festival of Rotterdam?",
        "options": [
            "RRR",
            "Bad Girl",
            "Piku",
            "Lagaan",
            "The Lunchbox"
        ],
        "answer": "Bad Girl"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country\u2019s students won the Bronze at the Global M-Gov Awards 2025?",
        "options": [
            "USA",
            "India",
            "Canada",
            "Japan",
            "Australia"
        ],
        "answer": "India"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who from Rajasthan has been shortlisted for the USD 1 million GEMS Education Global Teacher Prize 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Mohammad Imran Khan Mewati",
            "Dr. Ramesh Kumar",
            "Shalini Gupta",
            "Rajesh Kumar",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Mohammad Imran Khan Mewati"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who won the Tata Steel Masters Chess Tournament 2025 by defeating D Gukesh in the tiebreaker?",
        "options": [
            "Vincent Keymer",
            "R Praggnanandhaa",
            "Arjun Erigaisi",
            "Wei Yi",
            "Magnus Carlsen"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is the Indian-origin artist who won the Grammy Award for Best New Age, Ambient, or Chant Album in 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Ricky Kej",
            "Anoushka Shankar",
            "Chandrika Tandon",
            "Radhika Vekaria",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been awarded the Sahitya Akademi Award 2024 in Dogri literature?",
        "options": [
            "Jitendra Udhampuri",
            "Chaman Arora",
            "Veena Gupta",
            "Sushma Rani",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which two films led the BAFTA 2025, each winning 4 awards?",
        "options": [
            "Conclave and The Brutalist",
            "Anora and The Brutalist",
            "Conclave and Anora",
            "The Brutalist and The Artist",
            "Conclave and The Artist"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was honored with the 2024 Hurun Industry Achievement Award for Financial Solutions Innovation?",
        "options": [
            "Vijay Shekhar Sharma",
            "Raj P Narayanam",
            "Nandan Nilekani",
            "Deepak Parekh",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was honored with the Vishalakshi Award 2025 for her contributions to education?",
        "options": [
            "Dr. Bhagyashree Patil",
            "Sudha Murthy",
            "Dr. Ranjana Agarwal",
            "Dr. Vandana Shiva",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which company won the Forward Faster Sustainability Award 2025 in the Water Resilience category?",
        "options": [
            "NTPC Ltd.",
            "Reliance Industries Ltd.",
            "Tata Power",
            "Adani Power",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "NTPC Ltd."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was recently awarded the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire (MBE) for contributions to UK-India business relations?",
        "options": [
            "Mukesh Ambani",
            "Gautam Adani",
            "Ratan Tata",
            "N. Chandrasekaran",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which contingent won the Best Marching Contingent (CAPFs/auxiliary forces) in the People's Choice Category during the Republic Day Parade 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Delhi Police Marching Contingent",
            "BSF Marching Contingent",
            "CRPF Marching Contingent",
            "ITBP Marching Contingent",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been honoured with the RK Srikantan Trust Award at the Sankranti Music Festival in Bengaluru?",
        "options": [
            "L. Subramaniam",
            "TV Gopalakrishnan",
            "Zakir Hussain",
            "Ravi Shankar",
            "Shankar Mahajan"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which contingent won the Best Marching Contingent (CAPFs/auxiliary forces) award in the Republic Day Parade 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Delhi Police Marching Contingent",
            "BSF Marching Contingent",
            "CRPF Marching Contingent",
            "ITBP Marching Contingent",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Delhi Police Marching Contingent"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which Indian organisation has bagged Subhash Chandra Bose Aapda Prabandhan Puraskar for disaster preparedness in January 2025?",
        "options": [
            "National Disaster Management Authority",
            "Coalition for Disaster Resilient Infrastructure",
            "Indian National Centre for Ocean Information Services",
            "National Disaster Management Authority.",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which steel organization received the 'Great Place to Work' certification by the Great Place to Work Institute for the period January 2025 to January 2026?",
        "options": [
            "Tata Steel",
            "JSW Steel",
            "Steel Authority of India Limited (SAIL)",
            "Vedanta Limited",
            "Hindalco Industries"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was recently honored with the Singapore Honorary Citizen Award for strengthening India-Singapore bilateral relations?",
        "options": [
            "Anand Mahindra",
            "Tarun Das",
            "Sunil Bharti Mittal",
            "N. R. Narayana Murthy",
            "Azim Premji"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has won Best Performance by a Male Actor in a Limited Series, Anthology Series, or a Motion Picture Made for Television at the Golden Globe Awards 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Adrian Brody",
            "Colin Farrell",
            "Tadanobu Asano",
            "Jeremy Allen White",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "How many Arjuna Awards for outstanding performance in Sports and Games were announced in 2024?",
        "options": [
            "20",
            "29",
            "32",
            "26",
            "35"
        ],
        "answer": "32"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which veteran filmmaker will receive the Padmapani Lifetime Achievement Award at the Ajanta-Ellora International Film Festival 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Mira Nair",
            "Aparna Sen",
            "Sai Paranjpye",
            "Shyam Benegal",
            "Vivek Rathore"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    }
]